<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and exact relation of the strange finding out of Moses his tombe, in a valley neere unto Mount Nebo in Palestina. With divers remarkable occurrences that happened thereupon, and the severall judgements of many learned men concerning the same. / Communicated by a person of quality residing at Constantinople, to a person of honour here in England, and by him permitted to be published, for the satisfaction of the ingenious.</title>
            <author>Chaloner, Thomas, 1595-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 41 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1805</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason 1660[3]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209017</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867927</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867927</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170236</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78519)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 208:E1660[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and exact relation of the strange finding out of Moses his tombe, in a valley neere unto Mount Nebo in Palestina. With divers remarkable occurrences that happened thereupon, and the severall judgements of many learned men concerning the same. / Communicated by a person of quality residing at Constantinople, to a person of honour here in England, and by him permitted to be published, for the satisfaction of the ingenious.</title>
                  <author>Chaloner, Thomas, 1595-1661.</author>
                  <author>Geōrgarinēs, Iōsēph, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 39, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.G. for Richard Lowndes, at the White Lion in St. Paul's Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657. [i.e. 1656]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Described by Anthony à Wood as a hoax and ascribed by him to Thomas Chaloner, 1595-1661. Also attributed to Ioseph Geōrgarinēs. Cf. Halkett &amp; Laing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb: 31"; the 7 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Moses --  (Biblical leader) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170236:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A True and Exact</hi> RELATION OF THE STRANGE FINDING OUT <hi>OF MOSES</hi> his TOMBE, In a Valley neere unto Mount <hi>NEBO</hi> in <hi>PALESTINA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With divers remarkable occurrences that happened thereupon, and the ſeverall judgements of many learned men concerning the ſame.</p>
            <p>Communicated by a perſon of quality reſiding at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to a perſon of Honour here in <hi>England,</hi> and by him permitted to be publiſhed, for the ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Ingenious.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. G.</hi> for <hi>Richard Lowndes,</hi> at the White Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170236:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170236:2"/>
            <head>THE STATIONER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome flying rumours re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating to the ſubject matter of this inſuing diſcourſe may poſsibly have come to thy eares; for the thing was not done in a corner. But there hath not any perfect narration of
<pb facs="tcp:170236:3"/>it been publiſhed, ſo far as I can learn, in any language. Beſides, the quality of the perſons from whom I have received it, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular circumſtances of places and perſons adde very much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to it, ſo that it would be abſurd to doubt of the truth of it amongst a cloud of witneſſes. Thou wilt find ſuch ſmoothneſſe of language joyned with ſuch ſolidity of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in theſe few pages, that I am confident thou wilt not repent either of thy coſt in buying, or thy paines in reading them.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170236:3"/>
            <head>A Relation from <hi>Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> how the Sepulchre of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> was lately found out at Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> and what was done thereupon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N <hi>October</hi> 1655. certain Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Chriſtians keeping heards of Goats upon Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> otherwiſe called the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Abarim,</hi> they often obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved divers of their Goats to ſtray from them, and not to return in two or three dayes; and when they did return, they would as often go aſtray again, and carry other Goats with them: they alſo obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170236:4"/>that the haire of theſe ſtraying Goats did yield a moſt odoriferous ſcent; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they were ſo highly taken, as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved diligently to ſearch their goings out, thereby to learn the true cauſe thereof. Whereupon ſome of them on a day, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing theſe erring goats, they brought them to a ſtupendious precipice, in the bottome whereof lay a moſt delicious val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, but of ſmall circumference, which ſome of theſe Goatherds had ſeen before, but never could find any means of entrance thereinto, ſo ſteep and unacceſſible were the incloſing mountains. But at that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, whether it were by any earthquake lately happening, very uſuall in thoſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys; or by the decay of the mountains themſelves; the rocks on each ſide had made ſuch ſhootings into the opening of the valley, as not onely the Goats (one of the beſt climbing creatures) but even the Goatherds themſelves uſed to ſuch diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult untrodden paths, found a deſcent into this almoſt bottomleſs valley. Here they refreſhed themſelves with the verdure of the graſs, the ſweetneſs of the ſprings, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170236:4"/>with ſuch courſe fare as they carried with them in their ſcrips. About noon when the Sun ceaſed to be a comforter, they retired themſelves under the ſhadow of a rock, thinking their Goats would have born them company; and wondering what ſhould become of them, towards evening they eſpied them coming one by one out of the cleft of a rock, which it ſeemed to them, had been alſo ſhaken by an earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake: for on the top of it they ſaw huge maſſy trees overturned, which by their long growth had ſo fixed their roots in the clefts of the rock, as with their weighty fall, they tore up much of the foundation whereon they grew. Coming to this cave, and firſt putting in their heads, there iſſued forth the moſt odoriferous favour that could poſſibly be imagined, and putting in their ſtaves to feel the bottom of it, they found it of no great depth, their ſtaves like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe participating of the perfumes. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they adventured to enter, and firſt groping about with their hands and with their ſtaves in this dark place, and after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering their eye-ſight, by the light
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170236:5"/>which entred at the paſſage which gave them admittance, they found the cave to be of a circular figure, and not above twelve foot the diameter. The floor, the ſides, &amp; the hollow roof, ſeemed to be more than the work of nature, and yet nothing appeared therein to be the work of man. At their firſt coming in, haſtily croſſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this dark place, they ſtumbled upon ſomething which lay thwart the middle, &amp; cauſing their fellowes to ſtand out of the light, they diſcovered a materiall which ſeemed to be a Tomb-ſtone, and that it lay upon an other which appeared to be hollow, thicker than the uppermoſt, but of the ſame figure every way, and curiouſly joyned or mortiſed one into the other, without any morter or ciment. It was nine foot in length, and two foot from the ground, being three foot broad, and all plain, ſaving that at that part which ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be the head of it, they felt two knobs, which bunched out in the faſhion of horns, and there were letters engraven thereupon, which for want of light, but chiefly of learning, they could not read.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170236:5"/>
            <p>Having ſatisfied themſelves herewith ſufficiently, they returned back to their fellowes, who much longed for their co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and acquainted them with the whole circumſtance of their ſucceſſe, wherewith they were infinitely pleaſed, eſpecially with the moſt delicious ſcent of their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell. And thinking it a buſineſs of more value than to be kept ſecret, they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed that one of thoſe who had been an eye-witneſs of the premiſſes, ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint therewith <hi>Mataxat,</hi> the Patriarch of the <hi>Maronites,</hi> whoſe reſidence is in a val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Mount <hi>Libanus,</hi> called <hi>[Kanobeen Kadiſcha Mir-jam]</hi> or the Monaſtery of S. <hi>Mary,</hi> who being throughly informed of what had happened, and admiring the ſweet ſcent which came from the poor mens garments, otherwiſe ſordid and naſty, he conceived this to be the monument of ſome perſon more than humane, and therefore had a longing deſire to have gone thither himſelf; but his great age and the difficulty of the way obſtructing his reſolution, he gave the charge thereof unto two Prieſts, who were his Chaplains,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170236:6"/>men in learning and underſtanding (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially one of them named <hi>Aben-uſeph,</hi> or father <hi>Joſeph</hi>) ſufficiently qualified. Who coming to the place by conduct of the Goat-herds, found every thing exactly true, as they had cauſed it to be related to the Patriarch. And moreover taking lights with them into the cave, they found thoſe knobs which the Goat-herds ſpoke of, and which ſtood as it were upon the head of the Monument, to be the ſimilitude of two horns, not much unlike thoſe of a Bull. But that which ſatisfied their curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity even to aſtoniſhment, was, that ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly viewing the Inſcription, which was in the Hebrew character, and Hebrew lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, they found it to be in effect [MO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES <hi>THE SERVANT OF GOD</hi>] with theſe joyfull tydings carrying with them the tranſcript of the Inſcription, they returned to the Patriarch; who ſeeing this Inſcription, and hearing the relation, was raviſhed therewith above meaſure. But the odoriferous ſcent which proceeded from their garments (which gave a ſweeter favorthan all the ſpices of <hi>India,</hi> or gumms
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170236:6"/>of <hi>Arabia</hi> could do) made theſe perſons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt venerable in the opinion of men of all Religions, whereof there is ſtore in the Turks dominions. Who hereupon, with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement, began to take notice of this miraculous Invention, far exceeding in their judgement that of the Holy Croſs, and ſome of every ſort of them, having firſt viewed the place, did earneſtly endeavour how they might convert it moſt to their own profit.</p>
            <p>And in the firſt place the <hi>Maronites,</hi> as the firſt inventers, petitioned <hi>Morat</hi> the <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> under whoſe juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction it lies, that they might have the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this holy place. But they being poor, although they had juſtice on their ſides, yet being not able to bribe, the Chriſtians the Greek &amp; Armenian Churches ſtept in &amp; offered great preſent ſummes and yearly ſalaries to <hi>Morat Baſhaw</hi> for the keeping of it; eſpecially the latter exceeded, who ingaged morever to build a Monaſtery there, which they would fortifie as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, to ſecure themſelves and Pilgrims from the aſſaults of the wild <hi>Arabs,</hi> who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170236:7"/>do grievouſly infeſt all thoſe quarters. The Friers <hi>Minors</hi> of the order of S. <hi>Francis,</hi> who reſide at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for the entertainment of the Weſtern Pilgrims, offered very largely, that they might have it, and that by the means of the French Ambaſſadour reſiding at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi> But the Jewes (who are very rich, and generally cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers and treaſurers to the Grand Signior in moſt of his dominions) ſtruck in with the Mufty and Viſier Baſhaw, offering great ſummes of money for the poſſeſſion of this Sepulchre, alledging, that of right it belonged unto them, <hi>Moſes</hi> being their Law-giver and countrey-man, whoſe laws the Chriſtians did unworthily pervert, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaining from marriage, being eaters of ſwines fleſh, and the moſt deteſtable Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters in the world. That it would adde much unto the Grand Signiors honour, and might be an addition unto his title, that he was Lord of the three famous Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chres of the three famous Prophets, <hi>viz.</hi> of the Prophet <hi>Mahomet</hi> at <hi>Medina,</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and laſtly of <hi>Moſes</hi> at Mount <hi>Nebo.</hi> That they did concur with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170236:7"/>the <hi>Muſſelmans,</hi> not onely holding Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage honourable, but own plurality of Wives and Concubines to be neceſſary; that they did beſides abſtain from ſwines fleſh, &amp; were ſo far from worſhipping of any Image, as they held it not lawfull to make any at all. Theſe reaſons of the Jews, but chiefly their large bribes did ſo prevaile, as in all probability they were likely to carry it. When ſuddainly and unlooked for the French Jeſuits (who have their Colledge at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>) interpoſed, firſt by taking off the Grecian and Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Chriſtians, by telling them how diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing this would be to Almighty God, who upon deſign had hid and buried the body of <hi>Moſes</hi> in ſuch a ſecret place, to the end that the Jewes ſhould never find his Sepulchre, leſt otherwiſe they might com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Idolatry thereto, and worſhip it. That this Sepulchre being thus found out in this laſt and worſt age of the world, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Idolatry rageth, in deſpite of Gods Commandements, who hath more often and more bitterly expreſſed his deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, than againſt any other ſinne
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170236:8"/>whatſoever, wherefore they meekly advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to deſiſt in their ſuite, offering to take off the Latine Church from perſiſting in their petitions, for the Guardianſhip of the Sepulchre, as alſo the <hi>Maronites,</hi> beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching them with teares that they would not reſiſt the will of God, nor be the means of diſcloſing his ſecrets. Hereto they anſwered, that they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as fit to keep the Sepulchre as any other whatſoever; but if the other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians would deſiſt, and that the Jewes might be taken off, they would acquieſce. The credit of the Jeſuits took off the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Church, and the Maronites being poor, and now in a ſort members of the Roman or Latin Church, gave over their ſuit. The Jews were eaſily denied their requeſt, not onely becauſe the Turks do deteſtably hate them, but moreover the Jeſuits had cunningly intimated to the Viſier Baſhaw, how dangerous it might prove to that State, to ſuffer the Jewes (who pretend right to the holy Land by inheritance, and look every day for a call to be reſtored to their ancient patrimony)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170236:8"/>to have any command therein: and the fortifying of that place againſt the inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the Arabs, without which they could not live in ſafety, and the multitude of Jews, who would come to viſite the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, would very much incourage them to act ſomething not convenient for the <hi>Othoman</hi> Empire to permit: but their beſt argument was good round bribes which they gave him. So in concluſion, <hi>Morat Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Damaſco</hi> had expreſſe order brought him by a <hi>Chiaus,</hi> from the Port of the Grand Signior, to ſee that the cave of the Sepulchre ſhould be ſtopped up, &amp; that none upon pain of death ſhould approch within certain miles thereof. In purſuance of which order, <hi>Morat Baſhaw</hi> commanded forthwith the Sanzjacks of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and of <hi>Saphetta,</hi> being the neareſt Sanzjackries which confine upon the place, to ſee it performed with diligence, who in obedience to the Firman ſent by the Grand Signior, did execute it accordingly.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170236:9"/>
               <head>How the Jeſuits practiced to ſteal away the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>MOSES,</hi> and to carry it into <hi>France,</hi> and how they were prevented.</head>
               <p>IF the Jeſuits had been as great enemies to Idolatry, and as carefull to obſerve the will of God, as they pretended, it had been a greater miracle than the diſcovering of this Sepulchre: but their aim was quite contrary; for no ſooner was the nine days wonder over, and the buſineſſe began to be huſhed, but they began to put that in practice, which was from the beginning their determination; which in effect was to ſteal away the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it for <hi>France,</hi> to place it in their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>le Fleche,</hi> whereby they propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to themſelves the gaining of infinite reputation in holineſs, beſides the accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of wealth by indulgences. To effect this (by the means of the French Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, now wholly Jeſuited) letters were directed to the French Conſuls reſiding at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170236:9"/>S. <hi>John de Acre,</hi> and at <hi>Rama</hi> in the Holy Land, whoſe chief trading there is for Cottons, and who being placed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed by the Ambaſſadour, were cloſe and diligent in executing of his commands; which letters were to this effect, That they ſhould diligently inquire amongſt the Emirs and Shecks of the Arabs (who are petty Princes in thoſe parts, and who in deſpite of the Grand Signior poſſeſſe moſt part of that countrey) if for a good reward in Dutch Dollers any of them would undertake to aſſiſt the Jeſuits in conveying of the body either to <hi>Acre</hi> or to <hi>Joppa,</hi> and there to put it aboord a French veſſel, which ſhould attend them to that purpoſe, where they ſhould deliver the body with one hand, and receive their moneys with the other. To this the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls anſwered, that upon making a triall hereof, they found the Arabs averſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, not onely for fear of too much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking the Turk againſt them, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the high eſteem they have of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> whom they call in their language <hi>[Moo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a Carym Alla]</hi> that is, <hi>Moſes the righteous of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170236:10"/>God,</hi> yet the Conſuls did aſſure them that there were another ſort of people inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe now wild parts; the remainder of thoſe Frenchmen brought in by <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> who are called <hi>Druſes,</hi> and who have ever ſince defended themſelves in the Mountains againſt the Turks and Saracens. But they have now loſt their Chriſtian Religion, and yet are not good <hi>Mahometans</hi> neither; retaining the eating of Swines fleſh, which makes them odious to the Turks, who thereupon call them <hi>Rafties,</hi> that is, Infidels, yet they wear a white Turbant, and neither fearing God, nor obeying man, they conceived them fit for any deteſtable villany. To theſe they had imparted the buſineſſe, and were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured to get a conſiderable number of them, for a good ſumme of Dollers, part to be paid in hand, the reſt when they had finiſhed their work. The Jeſuits concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved their buſineſs as half done when they heard theſe tidings. And thereupon with divers French Gentlemen and Merchants, who deſired to participate of the honour, they imbarqued at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170236:10"/>French veſſell bound for S. <hi>John de Acre,</hi> formerly called <hi>Ptolomais,</hi> pretending to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſit the holy Sepulchre, and the renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed places for ſanctity in and near <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> The wind favoured them ſo much, as they overſhot their Port, and forced them to <hi>Joppa,</hi> much nearer their Rendez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous than <hi>Acre,</hi> it being not above forty Italian miles from <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> At <hi>Rama,</hi> now called <hi>Ramula,</hi> they were kindly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the French Conſul, who gave them great aſſurance of the Druſes, and brought them on their way towards <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> where they were lodged in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent of <hi>Franciſcans.</hi> They came thither about Mid-lent, as they deſigned, having time enough betwixt that and Palm-ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, to work the Father Guardian, and the other Friers to be aſſiſtant to their deſign, and to compact with the Druſes both for their reward, and for the time and place of their meeting. For it is to be obſerved, that the Tueſday after Palm-ſunday, the Father Guardian with many of his Friers and all Pilgrims that will go, make a jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to waſh themſelves in <hi>Jordan,</hi> carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170236:11"/>Souldiers with them for their convoy; and this is once every year and no oftner, unleſs upon very extraordinary occaſion. The buſineſs being broken to the Father Guardian, called <hi>Padre Gregorio,</hi> an Italian by Nation, as were moſt of the Convent, he did no wayes approve of the buſineſs, alledging many reaſons againſt it, but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally that their Convent at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> would thereby be diſſolved, and all the Weſtern Chriſtians for ever debarred from worſhipping or viſiting the holy Sepulchre hereafter. Some thought it was partly out of envy, that the Jeſuits ſhould enjoy ſo great a treaſure, who are an order that theſe Franciſcans do not greatly reverence. Howſoever he agreed to hold his accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med journey, and to keep ſecret their plot, the Jeſuits aſſuring him, that the Druſes ſhould not touch a hair of his head, nor of any his Convent. Now the plot was thus laid, That the Jeſuits under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of carrying victualls and proviſions for their journey to <hi>Jordan,</hi> in which they alwayes lie out ſome nights, being to viſit other places in their return, ſecretly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170236:11"/>a coffin, fine linnen, and other things, wherein to wrap the body, and good mules for themſelves and companions in the plot to ride upon, which they meant ſhould ſerve them in their flight to the ſea-ſide, where the veſſel which brought them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Polacre of Marcelles attended their deſign, under colour of taking in Cottons. And leſt <hi>Joppa</hi> ſhould prove no ſafe port for their retreat, they ordered the Patron or Maſter of the Polacre, to take them in ſome few miles to the Northward there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, at the Caſtle of Pilgrims, a deſolate port at this time, &amp; therefore the fitter for their purpoſe. They had likewiſe ordered the Druſes to meet them well armed and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed near to <hi>Jerico,</hi> the moſt confining place to <hi>Jordan</hi> they knew of; which they ſo punctually performed, as the pilgrims were no ſooner arrived on the bank of <hi>Jordan,</hi> and ready to ſhip themſelves to enter the river, but theſe Druſes fell upon them with great outcries in the Arabick tongue, the better to delude the Turkiſh Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who commonly are yearly aſſaulted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170236:12"/>by the wild Arabs, in that very place, and theſe Druſes differing little from the Arabs in habit and feature, the Souldiers took them to be no other, never ſuſpecting the plot, but looked onely to defend themſelves, while in the mean time the Druſes ſeiſed upon the Jeſuits and their company, their mules, baggage, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they had, not touching the Father Guardian, nor any of his Convent, two onely excepted, namely, Frier <hi>Ciprian</hi> and Frier <hi>Juniper,</hi> who being lay-brethren, Frenchmen, and of the plot, they took with them, leaving the Pilgrims half ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped of their clothes. And being advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the benefit of the night which then approched, they forded <hi>Jordan</hi> (which is eaſy to do in moſt places without a miracle, being a River not navigable any where) and by midnight they arrived at the cave of the Sepulchre, being at the foot of Mount <hi>Nebo,</hi> the top whereof being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Piſgath,</hi> which is over againſt <hi>Jerice,</hi> from whence God ſhewed unto <hi>Moſes</hi> all the Land of Promiſe.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170236:12"/>
               <p>The Jeſuits conceived, that before the Pilgrims and father Guardian could return to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to give notice of what had paſſed, which could not be till the night following, and that the <hi>Sanziack</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing who had committed this inſolency, nor much caring, it being but upon a company of Gowers or misbelievers, as they call Chriſtians, they made no doubt, but that they might be ſhip'd out of their reach, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could be met with; wherefore letting their Mules and horſes of the Druſes to graze upon the fragrant hearbs of that little valley, they betooke themſelves to pluck down the entrance into the <hi>Sepulchre</hi> which was eaſier to be pull'd down, then to be made up. But ſee how their Ship did ſink, even in the entrance of the harbour. For the Jeſuits had brought with them from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> an old <hi>Janizarie</hi> called <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> who had ſerved them many years faithfully; without the company of one of which there is no travailing in <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>key.</hi> This man they had ſounded a farr off, to try if they could make him of their plot.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170236:13"/>But he not willing in his old age to leave his Country, religion, wife and children, they deſiſted. This and daily the words which he heard from the mouths of thoſe French Gentlemen and Merchants who being in the plot, were too laviſh of their tongues before him, who by reaſon of his long converſation amongſt the French, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood more of their language, then they were aware of. This with other matters of the like nature, made him ſtrongly to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the deſign. And thereupon acquainted the <hi>Sanziack</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> therewith, fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf alſo ill at eaſe, to the end he might not be invited to that journey. The <hi>Sanziack</hi> perceiving that <hi>Ibrahim</hi> was not able to make it out, and yet doubting the worſt, being of a more ſubtle braine then Turks ordinarily are (he being in truth a <hi>Renegado</hi> Chriſtian, a notable knave, and a Scottiſh-man borne; his right name being <hi>Sande Murrey,</hi> but upon his circumciſion he called himſelf <hi>Ram-Dam</hi>) he gave notice of his feares to <hi>Nazuffe</hi> the <hi>Sanziack</hi> of <hi>Saphetta,</hi> who was alſo a <hi>Renegado</hi> of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170236:13"/>and as cunning a knave as himſelf: adviſing him, that he ſhould give notice hereof to certain troupes of <hi>Spahees</hi> who lay graſing of their horſes on the other ſide of <hi>Jordane</hi> untill they recevied orders from <hi>Morat, Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Damaſco,</hi> to goe againſt the ſonne of <hi>Ipſheer Baſhaw,</hi> the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell <hi>Baſhaw</hi> of <hi>Aleppo.</hi> The Captaine of theſe <hi>Spahees</hi> called <hi>Jaffer-Aga,</hi> a good ſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and the cunningeſt knave of all three, forthwith poſſeſt himſelf by his ſcouts, of all the foords over <hi>Iordan,</hi> lying between the lake of <hi>Genazaret</hi> and the <hi>Dead ſea.</hi> And having got notice of the Jeſuits paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage (though unknown to them) he lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely followed with three hundred Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hees well armed with lances, ſwords, ſhields, bowes, arrowes, and piſtols, being beſides incomparably mounted upon A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabian horſes, knowing the paſſages of the country, and moſt aſſured that they could not eſcape him.</p>
               <p>In the meane time the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> with the help of their company, had laboured ſo effectually in the opening of the cave, as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170236:14"/>even tyred and dropping with ſweat they faintingly entered; being inſtantly reviv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſtrengthned again by the odori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous ſent which they found therein, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing far above all the perfumes, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any of them had before ſented, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cave and monument to be every way anſwerable to the report. They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with ſtrong wedges and leavers, (which they brought purpoſely with them) to attempt the lifting up of the upper ſtone. Wherein Frier <hi>Juniper</hi> and Frier <hi>Ciprian</hi> more acquainted with ſuch labour, then with ſaying of <hi>Maſſe,</hi> or preaching, wrought with great effect. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo much as having tried both ends, and one of the ſides to no purpoſe, they putting their ſtrength to the other ſide, it opened ſo eaſily, as if it had been done by its own accord. The reaſon of this they found after to be, that the coffin, the cover and the hinges which faſtened them together, were all of one intire ſtone, unſeparated from the rock which made the cave, without any ſupplement whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170236:14"/>Then the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and their company, as men pleaſed and over-joyed, not onely with the more than Aromatick perfumes which iſſued out of it, but alſo with the deſire of ſeeing ſo ſacred a ſpectacle, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon their knees with great devotion, with all the eyes and light they had, began to prie and ſpie into this ſacred monument. But after they had looked it over and over ten times for failing, and put in their hands to ſearch more nearly the bottom, they found in it juſt nothing; nay it was as clear as if it had been ſwept, waſhed, and rubbed, not an hour before their coming. The Jeſuits and their company being much in their dumps for the loſſe of their labour, their money, their time, and indeed their reputation, began to think of a way, ſince they could not carry the body, which was not to be found, yet how they might convey the tomb into <hi>France,</hi> &amp; ſo into their Colledge. But when they had conſidered that it was not onely fixt to the naturall rock, or rather of one individual ſubſtance with it, and that beſides they had brought
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170236:15"/>no engine capable to carry over <hi>Jordan</hi> and the mountains of <hi>Judea</hi> ſo weighty a burden, they thought of breaking it in peeces, and of conveying it peece-meale that way. Whileſt they were thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving of their buſineſſe, they heard from without a hideous noiſe of horſes and armes, intermixed with the voices of men, reiterating often theſe words <hi>[Alla-hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlo]</hi> which is as much in the Turkiſh language, as <hi>the Lord be praiſed,</hi> which was the Spahees acclamations, when they found they had ſo happily ſurpriſed their prey. Hereat the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> (as they had reaſon) conceived great feare, ſo did all their company; and frier <hi>Juniper,</hi> for all his name and the odoriferouſneſſe of the place, was not yet ſo ſweet as he ſhould be. In the midſt of their feares two bold Spahees entred the cave, with their lances in the one hand, and bright Semiters in the other, with the butt-end of their lances they beat them all out of the cave, and as they iſſued out, they were ſtrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by the other Spahees to the very
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170236:15"/>skin every man, being ſoundly beaten be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, and ſo brought to <hi>Joffer-Aga</hi> the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. In the mean time the Druſes (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt loſt their horſes, and themſelves not able to eſcape) ſubmitted to mercy, &amp; ſo being all bound two &amp; two together, with their arms behind them, they were ſent under conduct towards <hi>Saphetta,</hi> which is neer the lake of <hi>Genezaret,</hi> as well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that way lay the Spahees quarters, as for that it being neer to <hi>Damaſco,</hi> they might the better receive orders from <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat Baſhaw</hi> how to diſpoſe of them. In the mean time, <hi>Jaffer-Aga,</hi> with two onely entring the cave, with great reverence worſhipped at the Sepulchre, thanking Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God that he had made him an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument (though moſt unworthy) to ſerve him. And having cloſed again the Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre, by ſoftly letting the lid or cover of it to fall into the place where it ſeemed to be joynted, and cauſing divers great ſtones to be rolled againſt the entrance of the cave, he with the remainder of his horſe followed his company. By noon the next
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170236:16"/>day he overtook them, having gotten as far as <hi>Jordan,</hi> where giving to every one of the priſoners a loaf of bread, he bad them drink of the river untill it was dry. And ſo departing to his tents with the greater number of his Spahees, carrying with him all the ſpoils of the Jeſuits, he comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the reſt to convey them carefully unto the Sanzjacks of Saphetta; which they ſpeedily put in execution: the caſe in leſs than 24. houres being much altered with the Jeſuits, who the evening before did ride trumphantly over <hi>Jordan</hi> upon their mules, bravely guarded by their Druſes; now they and their<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> guards in bonds were forced to wade the flood, which yet paſſed not much their middle. And ſo they wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed themſelves <hi>per force</hi> in <hi>Jordan,</hi> which yet Frier <hi>Juniper</hi> had no more than need of.</p>
               <p>The concluſion of all was for the preſent, that <hi>Morat Baſhaw</hi> ordered the priſoners to be ſent to the gallyes at <hi>Tripoly,</hi> in which as ſlaves at the oare they were to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> there to receive
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170236:16"/>ſuch further puniſhment as the Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior ſhould appoint. The two Sanzjaks, <hi>Ram-dam</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Zanzuffe</hi> of <hi>Saphetta,</hi> the firſt was preferred ſub-Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaw of <hi>Noha</hi> at the mouth of the red ſea; the ſecond, ſub-Baſhaw of <hi>Sues,</hi> at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome thereof; they never truſting a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Renegado in any part of <hi>Europe. Ibra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him</hi> the Janizary was ſent for to <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> to be recompenced. And <hi>Joffer-Aga</hi> Captain of the Spahees, advanced in military preferment, with promiſe to be made a Baſhaw.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170236:17"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>How the Jeſuits were uſed at</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>and of the great queſtion that did ariſe there by men of all Religions, what was become of the body of</hi> Moſes.</head>
               <p>WHen newes came of theſe tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the port of the Grand Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior, the Jeſuits were much condemned by all ſorts of Religions. But the Jews took occaſion hereupon to invey bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly againſt the Chriſtians above all meaſure, affirming they were the moſt treacherous thieves that ever lived in the world. Having whileſt the Souldiers ſlept ſtoln out of the Sepulchre the body of Chriſt, and thereby made the ſecond error worſe then the firſt. That <hi>Alon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170236:17"/>de Albuquerque</hi> vice-Roy of <hi>Goa,</hi> had a deſign to have defaced the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of <hi>Mahomet</hi> at <hi>Medina Talna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi,</hi> and to have thrown his body into the red Sea, but was prevented by death. The like deſign had <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinando</hi> the Great, Duke of <hi>Tuſcanie,</hi> to have forced the Sepulchre of Chriſt from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and to have placed it in his Chappel of Saint <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renzo</hi> at <hi>Florence;</hi> but he dyed ere he could effect it. And now this late plot of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> in attempting to ſteale away the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> howſoever miraculouſly prevented, yet it argued the Chriſtians to be a people, not fit to be admitted into the Turkiſh Empire. The vulgar being much incenſed by theſe and the like cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, the French Embaſſador was neceſſitated to obſcure himſelf for diverſe dayes in the houſe of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours Embaſſadour. The French
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170236:18"/>Conſul of <hi>Rama</hi> ſhipped himſelfe in the <hi>Bolane,</hi> appointed to attend the deſign, and ſailed to <hi>Marſelles</hi> his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive country. The <hi>Padre Guardiano</hi> at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and his convent were in great trouble by <hi>Ram-dam</hi> the <hi>Sanz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacke,</hi> untill <hi>Ibrahim</hi> the <hi>Ianizarie</hi> had cleared them by the oath of a <hi>Muſelman,</hi> that they had no hand in the buſineſſe. The Druſes were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to the Galleys for 120. yeares. The Gentlemen and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants for great ſummes of money, obtained ſo much favour as to be perpetually baniſhed the Turkes dominions. The Jeſuits were ſent to the ſeven Towers, there to be put to ſome cruell death, their colledge to be raſed, and their order never to return into Turkey again.</p>
               <p>The great queſtion then was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the learned of all Religions at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> what was become of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170236:18"/>the body of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Some Dry-vines ſaid it was there where it pleaſed <hi>God,</hi> which ſatisfied the queſtion as little as if they had ſaid nothing. Some Arabs Philoſophers ſaid it was evapored <hi>in fumo;</hi> but the Greeks argued out of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that it was impoſſible in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to reduce the whole earthy part of any mans body to nothing; nay they went ſo farre, as though they acknowledged that God had created all things of nothing, yet whether he could reduce all things to nothing againe, they humbly ſubmitted to better judgements. They holding that as Creation was a worke of perfection, ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction a worke of imperfection, whereof the Deity was not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The Jewes laughed at this diſpute, and demonſtrated out of <hi>Rabbi David Kimche,</hi> and out of <hi>Rabbi Salomon Ben Jack,</hi> that ſome
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170236:19"/>thouſands of yeares agoe, the Angels who were placed Guardians of <hi>Moſes</hi> Sepulchre, were furiouſly aſſaulted by a Devil named <hi>Asmandeus</hi> and his wicked Angels, inſomuch as <hi>Moſes</hi> body was taken from that place, and carried God knowes whither; whereupon being asked by the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, which ſide got the victory? they anſwered they could not tell. And being farther demanded, why then did they labour ſo much to be <hi>Guardians</hi> of the place where his body was ſuppoſed to lye? they anſwered, for the ſame reaſons which mov'd the Chriſtians to be <hi>Guardians</hi> of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of Chriſt, wherein it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their faith to believe that his body had at the preſent any reſidence. Againſt this the Chriſtians of the Latin Church alledged the nineth verſe of St. <hi>Jude</hi>'s Ep. whoſe words are [<hi>Yet</hi> Michael <hi>the Angel, when con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170236:19"/>with the Divel, he diſputed with the Divel about the body of</hi> Moſes, <hi>durſt not bring againſt him a railing accuſation, but ſaid, the Lord rebuke thee.]</hi> Out of which and the twelfth of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> verſe the ſeventh, <hi>[And there was warres in heaven,</hi> Michael <hi>and his Angels fought againſt the Dragon, and the Dragon fought and his Angels, and prevailed not.]</hi> They did conclude, that the Divel did not carry away the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but that the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God had ſtill the tuition thereof, yet where, they did not know. But the Grecian, Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian, <hi>Coptie, Abiſsine, Jacobin, Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian, Maronite</hi> and <hi>Neſtorian</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did wholly oppoſe this Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, with whom joyned many Lutherans reſiding at <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> denying rhe Epiſtle of St. <hi>Jude</hi> to be Canonicall, but more
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170236:20"/>eſpecially venting their ſpleenes againſt the <hi>Revelation</hi> of S. <hi>John,</hi> ſaying that it was none of his, full of obſcurity, void of reaſon, and the title forged; that the Author of it was <hi>Cerinthus</hi> the Heretick; and neither of them were allowed to be Canonicall, untill the Council of <hi>Carthage,</hi> which was wholly ſubſervient to the Papacy three or four hundred yeares after Chriſt; being both of them before that time not onely diſputed againſt, but wholly gainſaid. Theſe differences did no wayes clear, but rather ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure the queſtion, in as much as the Mufty to try all parties, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to know the opinions of the Proteſtant Divines. <hi>viz.</hi> the Dutch, and the Engliſh. But the Dutch, whether to ſave charges, or that they though it needleſſe, and perhaps dangerous, maintained no Divines
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170236:20"/>amongſt them; the Engliſh excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed themſelves as a point they had not at all ſtudied, nor ever found in their books, and therefore refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves to the Aſſembly of Divines in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The queſtion reſted not ſo, for <hi>Nazuffe</hi> coming to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to be inveſted in his new govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Sues,</hi> brought with him a book written by one <hi>Jeconius Ben-Gad,</hi> a learned <hi>Rabbi,</hi> dwelling at <hi>Saphetta,</hi> which is an Univerſity of the Jewes, wherein he did main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that this Tombe was not the Tombe of <hi>Moſes,</hi> who delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but of another <hi>Moſes</hi> very famous for his piety, who lived according to the Jewes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, many hundred yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him. To make good his aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he maintained it to be moſt unbeſeeming the wiſdome of God
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170236:21"/>to hide the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and yet to write his name upon his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre; beſides, the Inſcription be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing witten in Hebrew characters, argued it to be of a farre later date: for it is well known to the learned, that the <hi>Jewes, Samaritans,</hi> and <hi>Canaanites,</hi> had anciently no other Character but the <hi>Phoenician</hi> untill the Jewes uſed the Hebrew Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, which was invented by <hi>Eſdras</hi> after the Captivity. And for the late miraculous opening of an entrance into this valley, no formerly known, that proceeded from the ignorance of the Goat-herds, and the Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Patriarch, who being Chriſtians do little underſtand the Topography of the Land of Promiſe. But the learned Jewes know this to be an ancient valley, called formerly <hi>Hamagiddo,</hi> of farre greater extent than at this preſent, and that not
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170236:21"/>foure hundred yeares paſt, it was almoſt wholly devoured by an Earthquake. That there was no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy found in the Sepulchre, was no wonder, ſeeing the Chriſtians upon their conqueſt of the Holy Land by <hi>Godfrey</hi> of <hi>Bulloigne,</hi> left no Tombe or Monument of the dead unſearched for treaſure, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly making havock and Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the dead bones, leaving empty Sepulchres. That they had attempted the breaking up of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> Tomb, upon great confidence of finding therein an ineſtimable treaſure; but were miraculouſly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by fire which iſſued out of it. Nay, their unſatiated cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe was ſuch, as they would not have ſpared the holy Sepulchre (as they call it) of their Saviour Chriſt, had they not conceived, that by reaſon of his poverty there could
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170236:22"/>nothing of value be buried with him; for the ſtrange faſtning of the upper ſtone to the nether, as hath formerly beene expreſſed, it will appeare to be no miracle, when it ſhall be remembred how uſuall it was anciently amongſt the Jewes ſo to do, and the Sepulchres of the Kings of <hi>Judea,</hi> yet remaining neere <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to this day teſtifie as much. As for the odoriferouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the place, it will be no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, when the ſweet-ſmelling Gummes and Aromatick Spices of wonderfull price, wherewith anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently they did intombe their dead, ſhall be called to minde. Neither could it in the laſt place ſavour of any thing but of infinite impiety, to conceive that the arm of the great God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhould in theſe laſt times be ſo weakened, as he could not defend the body of his ſervant
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170236:22"/>from an Earthquake, or keep from vulgar eyes his unſcrutable ſecrets. This book, though written (after the Jewiſh manner) with much bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe againſt the Chriſtians, did give exceeding ſatisfaction. So it is thought this buſineſs hath received its full period.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
